<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tls on My technical gists</title><link>https://dmachard.github.io/tags/tls/</link><description>Recent content in tls on My technical gists</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dmachard.github.io/tags/tls/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>CoreDNS: secure your DNSTAP streams with TLS</title><link>https://dmachard.github.io/posts/0053-coredns-dnstap-tls/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dmachard.github.io/posts/0053-coredns-dnstap-tls/</guid><description>This post explains how to enable TLS on outgoing dnstap streams with CoreDNS. Please refer to How to enable it on main dns servers to enable DNStap in basic way.
TLS is supported since the version 1.11
Enable Secure DNSTAP with CoreDNS Create working folder
mkdir securednstap cd securednstap Create the following config_coredns.conf in your working folder.
tls:// to use TLS 192.168.1.200:6000 is the IP/port address of your DNStap collector. skipverify: this setting ignore TLS verification, do not use this settings in production.</description></item><item><title>PowerDNS/dnsdist: how to configure TLS for outgoing dnstap stream using stunnel</title><link>https://dmachard.github.io/posts/0006-powerdns-dnsdist-dnstap-tls/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dmachard.github.io/posts/0006-powerdns-dnsdist-dnstap-tls/</guid><description>This post will detail how to wrap your outgoing dnstap stream with TLS using stunnel.
Table of contents Introduction Installation Configuration Systemd Introduction This tutorial assumes you have a working PowerDNS dnsdist server installed on a Centos/AlmaLinux with dnstap enabled. Also we will use the same user/group that dnsdist for stunnel. Any feedbacks will be appreciated to improve this tutorial.
Installation Install stunnel
yum install stunnel mkdir /var/run/stunnel chown dnsdist:dnsdist /var/run/stunnel Configuration Configure stunnel</description></item><item><title>PowerDNS/dnsdist: how to configure TLS for the API using stunnel</title><link>https://dmachard.github.io/posts/0005-powerdns-dnsdist-api-tls/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dmachard.github.io/posts/0005-powerdns-dnsdist-api-tls/</guid><description>This post will detail how to wrap your DnsDIST webserver/API and dnstap stream with TLS using stunnel.
Table of contents Purpose Installation Configuration Systemd Purpose This tutorial assumes you have a working PowerDNS dnsdist server installed on a Centos/AlmaLinux with webserver api. Also we will use the same user/group that dnsdist for stunnel. Any feedbacks will be appreciated to improve this tutorial.
Installation Install stunnel
yum install stunnel mkdir /var/run/stunnel chown dnsdist:dnsdist /var/run/stunnel Configuration Create a certificate.</description></item></channel></rss>